<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/4.5" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
		 id="improve" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/4.5 http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xsd/4.5/docbook.xsd">

	<title>Improve</title>

	<chapterinfo>
		<abstract>
			<para>The functions in the 'Improve' tree are all what we would
				describe as first class 'Data Quality functions'. They not only
				analyze a problem but also usually present a solution to it.
			</para>
		</abstract>
	</chapterinfo>

	<section id="synonym_lookup_transformer">
		<title>Synonym lookup</title>
		<para>
			The Synonym lookup transformation is a critical part of DataCleaner's
			ability to standardize and cleanse data. Using this component you can
			look up values in a
			<link linkend="synonym_catalogs">synonym catalog</link>
			and have it replaced with its master term, if it is found to be a
			synonym.
		</para>
		<para>Below is a screenshot of the synonym lookup's configuration
			panel:
		</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="transformer_reference_synonym_lookup.png"
					format="PNG" scalefit="1" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<para>
			The configuration of the Synonym lookup is simple:
		</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select the column to apply the lookup function to.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Use the 'Retain original value' option to determine if
					unmatched values (non-synonyms) should be retained or if a null
					value should be returned if there is no match.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Select the synonym catalog to use for lookups.</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>

		<para>
			If your synonym catalog contains all the allowed values for a
			particula column, it can be a good idea to uncheck the 'Retain
			original value' checkbox and then do a simple null-check on the
			resulting output column. If null values are found, it's because there
			are values in the column that the synonym catalog is not able to
			standardize.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="table_lookup_transformer">
		<title>Table lookup</title>
		<para>The table lookup transformer allows you to look up values in a
			different table. Any amount of columns can be used for mapping
			(lookup conditioning) and for outputting (the outcome of the lookup).
		</para>
		<para>The configuration screen for the table lookup transformer looks
			like this:
		</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="transformer_reference_table_lookup.png"
					format="PNG" scalefit="1" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<para>To make the mapping you need to select the target datastore,
			schema and table names. Once selected you will be able to select
			which columns to use for condition setting when looking up values.
		</para>
		<para>The semantics of the Table lookup are close to the semantics
			of a
			LEFT JOIN. If no lookup value is found, nulls will be returned.
			However, if multiple records are found to match the conditions, only
			the first will be returned.
		</para>
		<para>Note that the Table lookup will use a cache for looking up
			values, to avoid querying the target table for every incoming value.
		</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
